Guide to the Utility Workers Union of America, Local 1-2 Records WAG.131
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Utility Workers Union of America, Local 1-2 Records
Bulk, 1960-1990
1927, 1941-1995, (Bulk 1960-1990)
WAG.131
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
4.0 linear feet (5 boxes)
Local 1-2 of the Utility Workers Union of America evolved out of the Utility Workers Organizing Committee (UWOC) established by the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) in 1938. In 1946, with more than 180 locals organized nationwide, the UWOC transformed itself into the Utility Workers Union of America, CIO. The collection includes: by-laws, minutes, correspondence, election records, bargaining records, and general files from 1927 and 1941 to 1995.
Utility Workers Union of America. Local 1-2.
Provenance
The records were donated by the Local in the fall of 1997.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The history of Local 1-2 properly begins with the Utility Workers Organizing Committee(UWOC) established by the Congress of Industrial Organizations in 1938. Previous practice within the industry had been to have company unions, easily controlled by management. Organizing was facilitated in the New York area by a merger of older local companies (New York Edison, Bronx Gas, the New Amsterdam Company, Central Union Gas, Northern Gas and others) into the Consolidated Edison Company(ConEd). One year after the merger the AFL-affiliated IBEW obtained the right to represent ConEd employees, and soon issued charters to each of the seven company unions.
In 1940, after a bitter intra-union dispute in the IBEW between the newly organized utility workers and electrical workers, the ConEd employees pulled out of the international union. The seven utility locals constituted themselves as the Brotherhood of Consolidated Edison Employees. As a newly independent utility workers union, the body took the name Local 1-2, representing the separate identities of two major categories, plant and clerical employees, within ConEd. The governing Council of the Brotherhood included representatives of both categories of workers. The Brotherhood eventually came to represent all unionized workers at ConEd.
In 1945 the Brotherhood was invited to become part of the CIO's Utility Workers Organizing Committee; it would make a significant contribution to the size and power of this body. In 1946, with more than 180 locals organized nationwide, the UWOC transformed itself into the Utility Workers Union of America, CIO. Three of the top officers of the new international union came from New York's Local 1-2.
The first administration of Local 1-2 remained in office for seventeen years, with Paddy McGrath and Andrew McMann as president and Business Agent, and Richland and Marsini as Assistant Business Agents. The personal popularity of McGrath, combined with a system of elections which heavily favored the incumbents, assured the continuation in office of the old guard. In the mid-1950s challenges to the incumbents were mounted by a number of groups, including the United Social Club (Joe Murray), the Security Party (Jim Geoghegan), the Rider Avenue Committee (Sampson and McMann, who had split from the McGrath slate) and "Steam." At the same time, the insurgents attempted to change the by-laws, to replace the practice of system-wide elections and appointed business agents with section-based elections for Board members and business agents - and slates for top officers. In 1958, in a marathon caucus meeting at the New Yorker Hotel, the challengers finally got together and fielded a joint slate known as "The Coalition." In one of the first elections to be conducted by the American Arbitration Association; 16,000 out of 20,000 eligible voters participated. The ballots took several days to count and the opposition won by a substantial margin.
Despite a number of disputes and defections within the Coalition alliance, the new administration managed to remain in office until 1990, when a new insurgent group, the Justice Party turned them out after a hard-fought campaign. Against a backdrop of ongoing internal struggles, the Local also faced a number a challenges from the outside, and an uphill fight against ConEd's attempts to hold back wage increases, trim benefits, and shrink the workforce. Between 1958 and 1962 ConEd bought three power plants from the Transit Authority. Workers in these plants had been represented by Transport Workers Union, Local 101, and the transfer of the plants led to a battle between the TWU and Local 1-2 for jurisdiction over those workers. Local 1-2 emerged victorious, and thereby gained 2,000 members.
The Local has long faced serious health and safety issues, including high rates of cancer among members exposed to asbestos, PCB's, and other toxic substances, and severe injuries due to fire and explosions. There have also been debates within the union about discriminatory practices in ConEd hiring, about the use of nuclear power, and the constant threat of downsizing in the ConEd workforce. In 1968 the Local mounted a two-week strike, which resulted in a return to work with acceptance of the company's original offer. A more debilitating nine-week strike in 1983 resulted in losses for the union, and widespread dissatisfaction with the Local leadership among members. The company had responded quickly and effectively to the black-out threat, demonstrated its ability to run the system using supervisors and even handled a fire emergency in mid-town in record time. After the 1983 strike, the workforce, which had already declined from its 1958 peak of 25,000, was reduced through attrition to 13,000.
Hard times in the Local brought a new series of challenges to the leadership in the late 1980s. In the face of a serious threat from the Unity Party, headed by Mike Cotter, James Joy returned to the post of Business Manager of the Local after serving as International president. He arranged a temporary truce, creating a special post for Cotter - but strife continued, as the leadership sought to oust Cotter and a court-ordered election was held, which restored him to his post. A new round of by-laws changes resulted in the victory of the Justice Party, and its presidential candidate, John Goodman, in September 1990.
Sources:
For a more detailed history of the Local see the typescript survey report (Harry Van Arsdale Labor Records Project, Survey #387) produced by Jane Latour for the Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives in 1991.
Scope and Content Note
Series I: By-Laws (1962-1989; arranged chronologically).
This series includes both copies of by-laws and proposed by-laws, and a considerable amount of correspondence and publicity material reflecting the use of by-law changes by dissident groups in the Local to effect alterations in structure and leadership.
Series II: Minutes (1963-1989, arranged chronologically).
This series is divided into two parts, minutes of Executive Board meetings and minutes of General Membership meetings, each of which reflects the varied political concerns (both internal and external), industrial issues, and bargaining points confronting the Local over the past three decades.
Series III: Correspondence (1958-1987, arranged chronologically).
For the most part the Local officers correspondence has not been preserved. The few files in this series include only sporadic and for the most part trivial examples, as well as routine memos and publicity communications between the UWUA national and regional offices and the Local.
Series IV: Election Records (1960-1995, arranged chronologically).
This exceptionally rich series documents the contentious election history of the Local. Although the notorious 1958 election, which unseated the McGrath administration is not covered, later elections are well represented through leaflets, memos, clippings, ballot tallies, and official reports of arbitrators and court-appointed monitors.
Series V: Bargaining Records (1958-1993, arranged chronologically).
Bargaining files, agreements and arbitration awards in this series documents not only the major points of contention between ConEd and Local 1-2, but also reflect the continuing pressure from dissident groups against the leadership of the Local. Leaflets and typescript memos and reports calling on members to reject various "packages" proposed by the Local leadership are especially noticeable in the files for 1983 and 1989. There are some gaps in the series, including Bargaining Files for the strike year of 1968.
Series VI: General Files (1927; 1941-1994, arranged alphabetically).
This series includes both correspondence and a wide variety of printed materials illustrated many aspects of local union activity, as well as general subjects related to the industry, or to the interests of individuals officers. Intra-union affairs are represented in files on African-American and Cuban workers at ConEd, efforts by the Progressive Labor Party to influence Local members, Local financial records, and legislative files. Several files record the Local's dealings with individual employers other than ConEd (small numbers of Local members were employed by private companies). Several files from the 1940s detail organizing efforts within ConEd which resulted in the replacement of older company unions by the Brotherhood of Consolidated Edison Employees.
Arrangement
Organized into 6 series: Series I - By-laws (1962-1989); Series II - Minutes (1963-1989); Series III - Correspondence (1958-1987); Series IV - Election Records (1960-1995); Series V - Bargaining Records (1958-1993); Series VI - General files (including correspondence and printed materials, 1941-1994).
Series I-V are arranged chronologically and series VI is arranged alphabetically.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Records of the Transport Workers Union of America (including TWU Local 101).
See also, The Record, the newspaper of Local 1-2.
Separated Material
Six linear feet of photographs were separated from this Collection and are now in the Non-Print Department of the Wagner Archives/Tamiment Library.
Twelve reel-to-reel tapes of UWUA conferences are in the Oral History Collections of the Library.
American Federation of Labor.; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.).; Consolidated Edison Company of New York, inc.; International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers.; Utility Workers Organizing Committee.; Arbitration, Industrial.; Ballots.; Bylaws (administrative records).; Clippings (information artifacts).; Collective labor agreements |x Public utilities.; Correspondence.; Election returns.; Electric industry workers |x Labor unions.; Financial records.; Fliers (printed matter); Labor unions |x Elections |z New York (State) |z New York.; Labor unions |x Officials and employees.; Labor unions |x Organizing |z United States.; Minutes.; New York (N.Y.); Newsletters.; Records (documents); Strikes and lockouts |x Public utilities |z New York (State) |z New York.
- Series I: By-Laws, 1962-1989
  - By Laws: Proposed Amendments, 1962, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - By Laws: Proposed Amendments, 1984, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - By Laws: Proposed Amendments, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - By Laws: Proposed Amendments, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: Minutes, 1963-1989
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jan 1, 1964-May 31, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jun 1, 1964-Dec 31, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jan 1, 1965-May 31, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jun 1, 1965-Dec 31, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jan 1, 1966-Jun 30, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jul 1, 1964-Dec 31, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jan 1, 1967-May 31, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jun 1, 1967-Dec 31, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jan 1, 1968-Aug 31, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Sep 1, 1968-Dec 31, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jan 1, 1974-Jun 30, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jul 1, 1974-Dec 31, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, May 28, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, May 29, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, May 30, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, May 31, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jun 1, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jun 2, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jun 3, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jun 4, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jun 5, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jun 6, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jun 7, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jun 8, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jun 9, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jun 10, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jan 1, 1989-Jun 30, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, Jul 1, 1989-Dec 31, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Minutes -Membership Meetings, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Minutes -Membership Meetings, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Minutes -Membership Meetings, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Minutes -Membership Meetings, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Minutes -Membership Meetings, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Minutes -Membership Meetings, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Minutes -Membership Meetings, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Minutes -Membership Meetings, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Minutes -Membership Meetings, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Minutes -Membership Meetings, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1958-1987
  - Correspondence: Officers, undated, 1960-1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: UWUA, 1958-1964 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: UWUA, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: UWUA, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: UWUA, Region 1, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: UWUA, Region 1, 1962-1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Election Records, 1960-1995
  - Election, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Election, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Election, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Election, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Election, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Election, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Election, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Election, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Election (I), 1990 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Election (II), 1990 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Election, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Series V: Bargaining Records, 1958-1993
  - Bargaining, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Bargaining (I), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Bargaining (II), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Bargaining (III), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Bargaining (IV), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Bargaining (Settlement), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Bargaining (I), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Bargaining (II), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Bargaining (III), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Bargaining (IV), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Bargaining (V), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Bargaining (I), 1962 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Bargaining (II), 1962 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Bargaining (III), 1962 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Bargaining, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Bargaining, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Bargaining, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Bargaining, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Bargaining, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Bargaining, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Bargaining, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Bargaining, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Agreement, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Agreement, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Arbitrations (I), 1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Arbitrations (II), 1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Arbitrations, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Arbitrations, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Arbitrations (I), 1978 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Arbitrations (II), 1978 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Arbitrations (I), 1979 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Arbitrations (II), 1979 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Arbitrations, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Arbitrations, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Arbitrations, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Arbitrations, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Arbitrations, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Arbitrations, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Arbitrations, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Arbitrations, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Arbitrations, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Arbitrations, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Series VI: General Files, 1927-1994
  - Asplundh Tree Expert Company, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Black Solidarity Alliance, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Brotherhood of Consolidated Edison Employees: Newsletters; Local 3 and Local 5, 1941-1942 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Coalition Committee (Local 369, Boston), 1959-1963 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Con Ed Employees Mutual Aid Society, 1948, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Con Ed Environmental Policy, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Con Ed Organizing, undated, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Convention (UWUA), 1963 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Cuban Workers Party of Con Ed, ca.1970s (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Dickey-Lincoln Bill, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Expenditures, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Expenditures, undated-1985 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Federation of Utility Employees, 1942-1968 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Fiftieth Anniversary: Souvenir Program, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Asplundh Tree Expert Company, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Black Solidarity Alliance, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Brotherhood of Consolidated Edison Employees: Newsletters; Local 3 and Local 5, 1941-1942 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Coalition Committee (Local 369, Boston), 1959-1963 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Con Ed Employees Mutual Aid Society, 1948, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Con Ed Environmental Policy, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Con Ed Organizing, undated, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Convention (UWUA), 1963 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Cuban Workers Party of Con Ed, ca.1970s (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Dickey-Lincoln Bill, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Expenditures, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Expenditures, undated,1985 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Federation of Utility Employees, 1942-1968 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Financial Statements, 1983-1985 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Financial Statements, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Financial Statements, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Financial Statements, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Job Bulletins, 1980s (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Legal Fees, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Legislative and Cope Committee, 1970s (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Mc Mahon, J.: Irish Materials, 1949-1979 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Manual Underground Cable System, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Progressive Labor Party, undated, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Rate Hearings, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Regional Conference, Dec 9, 1966-Dec 10, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Report on Health Impact on Low Level Radiation, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Retirement Plan, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Safety Grants, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Security Party Highlights, 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - S.G. Blakly Tree Company, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Tree Preservation Company, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Truth-in-Lending, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - UWUA Region 1, undated, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 34)